Guide to the Lessons of the Sixties: A history of local Washington, DC activism for peace and justice from 1960-1975: Interviews, 2010-2019 MS2388
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Interview: Huff, Julie, 2016 August 11; MS2388
  Keywords provided by the donor for Julie Huff interview: public health nurse, born and raised in deep south, Birmingham Alabama until age 13, Atlanta Georgia until college, 1950s idyllic childhood, segregated but economically diverse public school, bookish child intellectual, civil rights movement, Bull Conner, sneak out to rallies and hootenanies, campaigned for Lyndon Johnson, Governor's Honors Program – first integrated student program in Georgia – between sophomore and junior years, Macon Georgia, stares, spit, menace, radicalizing experience, TWTWTW – that was the week that was – skit got advisor fired, New College in Sarasota Florida, culture shock, housing co-op conference in DC in senior year, intentional community, sexual harassment from two male friends, clinically depressed, moved to DC – District of Columbia, intentional housing – shared everything – rent food cloths, anti-war activist, women's movement, consciousness raising, imperialism, WITCH – Women's International Terrorist Conspiracy from Hell, United Fruit, guerrilla theater, birth control pills, abortion counseling, Off Our Backs, column – The Garbage and the Flowers, librarian, waitress, pregnant February 1970, not ready for a child, New York only safe place for abortion, DC required psychiatric assessment of threat to mother's health, private hospitals – pro forma process, DC General Hospital refused therapeutic abortions, lead plaintiff in class action lawsuit against DC General, injunction, several court hearings, back-up plan: private doctor at George Washington University, two psychiatric letters, humiliating, attest to wanting to kill herself, dupe of ACLU, felt no shame, support of women's movement, worse today, diaphragm, contraceptive failure, pill caused migraines, Washington Free Clinic, Mary Doe et. al. Plaintiffs vs General Hospital of District of Columbia, judge ruled against March 1970, final victory 1974, William Nussbaum and Carolyn Nickerson - lawyers, women's health, women's theater, Earth Onion Theater Group, workshops for women's empowerment, Black Box poetry magazine, ACLU prison project, nursing school – Catholic University, women's health and public health for over 30 years, Arlington County, lessons – find partnerships with people and organizations, Venceremos Brigade 1971, cut sugarcane, toured Cuba, democracy spring for campaign finance, people's lives on the line, role of draft in anti-war movement, Black Lives matter, gun violence, gun control activism.
- Interview: Kranz, Sharlene, 2015 August 25; MS2388
  High school civil rights activist who staffed the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party (MFDP) office in Washington, D.C. during the summer of 1964, when the MFDP challenged the legitimacy of the Mississippi delegation at the Democratic Party convention in Atlantic City. Also, an early member of Jews for Urban Justice.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Sharlene Kranz interview: Worker bee, middle school, union activities, activist family, SNCC at Howard U.,SNCC Conference 1963, STUDENTS AGAINST DISCRIMINATION, Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, Fannie Lou Hamer, Scherner and Goodwin and Chaney, Rita Scherner, Democratic Convention 1964, Joseph Rauh, Eleanor Holmes, SNCC New York, SNCC Washington, Marion Barry, bus boycott, white members of SNCC, housing, covenants, ACCESS, Charlie Jones, military bases, segregated housing, Maryland and Virginia apartments, 1968 Fair Housing Law, Jews for Urban Justice, anti-ICBM, grape boycott, anti-war.
- Interview: Kuntzler, Paul, 2016 February 12; MS2388
  Paul Kuntzler has been one of the most influential figures in the Washington, D.C. gay rights movement for well over 50 years. No one, aside from Franklin Kameny, the founder of the D.C. Mattachine Society, has had a bigger impact over the last 5 decades. From his membership on the board of the Mattachine Society at age 19, to the first gay rights protest at the White House in 1965, to his roles in the establishment of the Gay and Lesbian Activists Alliance, the creation of the Getrude Stein Democratic Club, and the development of the gay/lesbian community into one of the city's most potent political forces, Paul has been in the forefront of the movement right on down to the present day.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Paul Kuntzler interview: Washington, D.C. Gay Rights Movement, Paul Kuntzler, Franklin Kameny, Mattachine Society, White house first gay protest April 1965, Gay Activists Alliance, Gertrude Stein Democratic Club, Detroit, Grosse Pointe Woods, Michigan, large Catholic family, United Auto Workers, working class family, Detroit News, St. Joan of Arc Grade School, Notre Dame High School, 1952 and 1956 Republican and Democratic conventions, Adlai Stevenson, Sen. Estes Kefauver, John F. Kennedy, Anchorage, Alaska, Detroit Metropolitan Airport, pictured with JFK, Detroit News, Donna Kuntzler, campaigned for JFK, Dennis Reck??? Rudd?, Grosse Pointe Young Democrats, 14th congressional district headquarters, door-to-door, JFK's inauguration, Young Democratic Inaugural Ball, Mayflower Hotel, Lyndon Johnson, Lady Bird Johnson, Bobby Kennedy, Grosse Pointe Young Democrats, Toledo, Ohio, Greyhound Bus, Hollywood, gay people go Toledo, New Year's Eve, 3.2 beer in Ohio at 18, The Scenic (Bar), Toledo, The Pink Elephant (D.C. gay bar), Mayflower Hotel, Harrington Hotel, Carol's (Bar), D.C., Dupont Circle, Copper Skillet, N and Connecticute, Doug Tate, Gabe Price CHEKK, forst gay party, Georgetown Grill, Chicken Hut, Johnny's, first 3 main gay bars in D.C., E.J. McDevitt's card shop, The Homosexual in America (book), Bellevue Stratford Hotel, Doug Tate, Jesse Stern (author), The Sixth Man (book), gay rights movement, Statler Hilton Hotel, Hartman Hall, rooming houses, Scholl's Cafeteria, Washington Post, Union Trust Company, openly expressed racism, Union Trust whites-only hiring, Silver Spring, Md., Paul Levine, Giant (supermarket), Chicken Hut, Howard, Bill Fly, manager, Dr. Franklin Kameny, Mattachine Society, Adams Morgan neighborhood, Earl Aikins (sp?), Mattachine board of directors, Janus Society, Daughters of Bilitis, Barbara Gittings, Golden Gate YMCA, Hal Kall, San Francisco Mattachine Society, Frank Kameny, Court of Appeals brief, homophile literature, Dr. Evelyn Hooker, gays, lesbians prohibited working, federal government, D.C. government, security clearances, American Psychiatric Association, homosexuality mental illness, Bruce Scott, Frank Kameny, Robert Dellinger, Philadelphia, Barbara Gittings, planning conference, ECHO, East Coast Homophile Organization CHEKK, Frank Kameny, All the Way Home (Kuntzler short story), Scott fired, Department of Labor, because gay, Frank Kameny, disorderly conduct, U.S. Navy Map Service, Kameny fired because gay, Edgar Hoover and gays, Mattachine Society, Frank Kameny -- co-founder, Ph.D Harvard-astronomy, Jack Nichols -- co-founder, April 17, 1965, first anti-Vietnam War demonstration (SDS), also first White House gay rights protest, 7 men, 3 women protesters, Jack Nichols, Frank Kameny, Lily Vincennes, Gail Green, Robert Dellinger, ABC television network, Afro American newspaper, picketed State Department, U.S. Civil Service Commission, Secretary of State Dean Rusk, Office of Naval Intelligence, Stephen Brent Miller, Chicken Hut, Stenotype Institute of Washington, House Appropriations Committee, All Souls Unitarian Church, Dean Duncan Howlett, John Kennedy, RKO Keith's Theater, Old Ebbitt Grill, The Children's Hour, Shirley Maclaine, Audrey Hepburn, Lillian Hellman, D.C. Transit, Roy Chalk, Frank Kameny, George Washington University Hospital, Volkswagen, Rehoboth Beach, Delaware, Philadelphia, First Gay rights Picket, Independence Hall, Avenue Restaurant, Richard Davidson, Randy Wicker, John James, LGBT Retirement Home, Philadelphia, PBS, Washington Post, New York Times, Independence Hall, Philadelphia Pops Concert, Philadelphia Mayor Michael Nutter, Mattachine Society, Bill Donovan, Office of Naval Intelligence, Chicken Hut, Central Intelligence Agency, Frank Kameny, Barbara Gittings, "Gay Is Good", ECHO (East Coast Homophile Organizations), Dr. Albert Ellis, APA, Sheraton Wardman Park Hotel, Wardell Pomeroy, Kinsey Institute, American Nazi Party, Rabbi Eugene Lipman, Barbizon Plaza, Lillian Vincennes, Mattachine Society, confrontation tactics, Jim Foster, Alice B. Toklas Gay Democratic Club (San Francisco), 1972 and 1976 Democratic National Conventions, David Carliner, Bruce Scott, National Capital Area Chapter ACLU, Office of Naval Intelligence, Hoover Reporting Company, Don Crawford, Perry Redford, pseudonyms, Mattachine Society, Paul LeMay (alias), Frank Kameny, Bruce Scott, Stonewall, JFK assassination, Vietnam War, anti-war movement/demonstrations, civil rights movement, Martin Luther King Jr., March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom, United Auto Workers, I Have a Dream Speech, General Ulysses S. Grant, Civil War, Georgetownn University, New Hampshire, campaign for Senator Eugene McCarthy, Lyndon Johnson, Indianapolis, Bobby Kennedy, Martin Luther King, Jr., Gay Activist Alliance, Gertrude Stein Democratic Club, Marion Barry, Channing Phillips, Mattachine Society, Rev. Walter Fauntroy, Alan Hoffert, memorandum Frank Kameny for Congress, Richard Davidson, Lynn Burnett, Frank Kameny, Gay Liberation Front, Frank Kameny's campaign, David Carliner, Georgetown University students, Pennsylvania students, Gay Activist Alliance of New York, Safeway groceries, Temple Sinai, Gay Liberation Front, District Building, Alan Hoffert, Tony Jacobowski, Serta Mattress, Paul Newman, Joanne Woodward, gay political influence D.C., the gay community, Gertrude Stein Democratic Club, Marion Barry, Paul Newman, Joanne Woodward, Gay Activist Alliance of New York, Gay Activist Alliance of Washington, D.C., Jim Clark, Joel Martin, Jim Foster, Alice B. Toklas Democratic Club, San Francisco, Gertrude Stein Democratic Club, Gay and Lesbian Activist Alliance, David Goodstein, The Advocate (L.A. gay newspaper), Gay Rights National Lobby, Frank Kameny, Marion Barry, Mayor Walter Washington, Sterling Tucker (D.C. Council chairman), Marion Barry, won due to gay support, Gertrude Stein Democratic Club, Frank Kameny, Gay Rights National Lobby, Human Rights Campaign Fund, The Fund for Fairness, Walter Mondale, Tony Randall, The Plus-One (D.C. bar), University of Virginia (Northern Virginia campus), Stonewall, National Convention Project, first gay rights plank, 1980 Democratic national convention, Melvin Boozer, anti-discrimination laws, gay marriage.
- Interview: Landau, Saul, 2012 October 19; MS2388
  (1936-2013) - Internationally known scholar, author, commentator, and filmmaker who worked for 40 years on social, political, and human rights issues. He produced more than 40 films, and won several awards, including an Emmy. Among his D.C.-produced films was the Edgar Allan Poe Award-winner, "Assassination on Embassy Row," an investigation into the mid-'70s murders in Washington of exiled Chilean Ambassador Orlando Letelier and his Institute for Policy Studies colleague, Ronni Moffitt.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Saul Landau interview: Censorship, Jean Genet, Oakland, Berkeley, 1972 came to D.C., film projects at IPS, CLR James, Who Shot Alexander Hamilton, A Song for Dead Warriors, less activism in D.C. vs Berkeley, The New Radicals with Paul Jacobs – 1966, KQED public radio, Losing Just the Same, Report from Cuba, From Protest to Resistance – on the movement, Mario Savio, Stokeley Carmichael, David Harris, participating in and filming civil rights and anti-war movements, Fidel – 1968, 1969 right-wing Cubans bombed and burned theaters in NY and Los Angeles to block showing of Fidel, work with Congress, Senator Jim Abourezk, Congressman Phil Burton – best organizer in Congress, Congressman Walter Jones, Father Drinan, Congressman Chuck Whalen, Watergate hearings, IPS people worked as staff in Congress, Orlando Letelier, Ronni Moffitt, bomb, Augusto Pinchet, Cointelpro, ran agents into IPS, Karl Hess – Libertarian – IPS fellow, IPS sued FBI and won, wiretapping Marc Raskin's office, film with Robert Wall – former FBI agent, proud of five children, Will the Real Terrorist Stand Up, Sixth Sun: Mayan Uprising in Chiapas, Subcomandante Marcos, 1970s: Washington D.C. a Black city, most visitors never saw real city, Letelier, Tatia Allende.
- Interview: Lesser, Roger, 2015 October 05; MS2388
  Social worker, antiwar activist, early IPS Fellow.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Roger Lesser interview: American Labor Party, union organizing, FBI, Smith Act, Julius and Ethel Rosenberg, Furniture Workers Union, Dow Chemical, Paul Robeson, IPS (Institute for Policy Studies), Appalachia, Off Our Backs.
- Interview: Malcolm Davis Remembered, 2013 October 10; MS2388
  (1937-2011) - Ecumenical campus chaplain at GWU from 1967 until 1984. Throughout the late 1960s-early 1970s, Mal Davis's campus office served as a gathering and planning spot for civil rights and antiwar activists. Davis personally fought for social justice -- in the South organizing civil rights bus caravans and sit-ins, leading voter registration drives, confronting the Ku Klux Klan; in D.C. helping organize the Poor People's Campaign and its accompanying Resurrection City in 1968, and helping organize anti-war protests during the Vietnam War. He later became renowned for his porcelain pottery.
  Interview participants include Sally Benbasset Tim Frasca Lexi Freeman Richard Lipsitz Esther Siegel George Virkus. All of whom were student activists at George Washington during the late 1960s and early 1970s.
  Kerywords provided by the donor for Malcolm Davis interview: Lessons of the Sixties, bio of Mal Davis, George Virkus was a C.O., Timothy Frasca was a curious freshman, Richard Lipsitz participated in the huge demonstrations of the fall of 1969, Sally Benbasset volunteered at St. Elizabeth's and did abortion counseling, Alexa Freeman moved from anti-war to the Women's movement, Esther Siegel tutored at St. Elizabeth's, religion at George Washington University, death of Martin Luther King, civil rights, George Washington University, attitude of the university, attitude of Davis' board, range of activities, Jewish Defense League, Palestine, SDS actions, draft center, Malcom as a mature voice, SERVE office as a home, active rally and disobedience, compassion, class attendance, class content, 1971 was peak, Nixon's second inauguration, women's movement, exclusivity, People's Union welcomed all, "with us or against us" elsewhere, personal counselor, May Day 1971 anecdotes, arrests, civil disobedience, settlements for illegal arrest, Moonies, Unification Church, informants, Mal didn't criticize people, group house, 1405 21st St, draft counseling, overnight military guests, pot and acid, marijuana and LSD, prison guard experiment, P Street beach, Mad Dog, parents, community radio, Pacifica Radio, Santiago Chile, AIDs, Labor Union work, abortion counseling, OFF OUR BACKS, parent cooperative daycare, radical feminism, Institute for Policy Studies, working for Mal, weddings, later life as a potter, the mimeograph machine.
- Interview: Malone, Joann, 2016 January 15; MS2388
  Joann Malone was a member of the Sisters of Loretto for almost twelve years, her first teaching assignment beginning in Montgomery Alabama in 1963. The Civil Rights Movement transformed her into an activist for life in efforts to end poverty, war, racism and sexism. After hearing Thich Nhat Hanh speak in 1968 about the war in Vietnam, she joined the DC-9 in an action in DC against Dow Chemical's production of napalm, nerve gas and defoliants. Her "claim to fame" is being the first nun in US history to commit five federal felonies, be convicted and face 35 years in prison. Once the DC area became a permanent home, she continued working with revolutionary groups, organizing unions at area factories and hospitals and teaching Social Studies in DC and MD public high schools for twenty-one years. She worked at IPS on a prison project, wrote for Off Our Backs, was a member of the DC Unite to Fight Back and of Earth Onion Women's Improvisational Theater.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Joann Malone interview: Joanne Malone, Radical nun, Sisters of Loretto, Progressive religious order, Mother house in Kentucky, Sister Luke Tobin, Social action in the church, Thomas Merton, Liberation theology, Pedagogy of the Oppressed, Vatican II, Federal Felony charges, Birmingham bombing, Montgomery, AL, Kansas City, MO, Ending racism, 1964-67, 1969 Dow Action, Anti-war movement, Poverty in Kansas City, War images on television, Black Liberators, Police arrests, Baltimore 4, Phil Berrigan, Tich Nat Hanh, Catonsville 9, Civil Disobedience, Dow Chemical Office, D.C. 9, Blood on files, Publish in Times and Washington Post, Link between government and Dow Chemical, Draft action, Women's detention, Fasted while in jail, Started a journal while in jail, Lawyers, Charged with 5 federal felonies, Probation, Feb 3-10 1970, 1973 won in appeal, Pleaded guilty to one misdemeanor, Act according to our conscience, New School phD program, Earth Onion Theater Group, Art and Irene Waskow, IPS, Off Our Backs, Commune in D.C., Study Group, Left the church in 1967, DC Unite to Fight Back, U.S. China People's Friendship Association, Free Terrence Johnson, Georgetown University Hospital Union Organizing, Single Mother, Revolutionary change, One priest sentenced to 9 years, Anti-nuke movement in 1970's, Our children carrying out fights against racism and other important issues, Teaching Peace Studies in Montgomery School System, Montgomery Blair and Wilson High Schools, Student walkout to protest bombing of Iraq, Agent Orange, PTSD, Alcoholism, Opportunities for women, Women's Movement, Police Brutality, Militarization of police, Live Your life, Mindfulness Meditation, Trip to Vietnam with Tich Nat Hanh, Cambodia, Poverty throughout the world, Courage to act, Act for peace, Vietnam Boat People, Need compassion for everyone, Meditation retreats, Lessons for Young People, A vision of peace, Love is the answer.
- Interview: Margolies, Richard, 2015 March 18; MS2388
  Richard Margolies was a conscientious objector during the Vietnam War and participant and chronicler of the intentional community movement with its values of sharing and equality that blossomed during the 1960s and 1970s. He later had a long career as a clinical psychologist.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Rick Margolies interview: Handbook for Conscientious Objectors, draft card, conscientious objector status and public service, Freedom of Information Act, FBI, Margolies as "dangerous person," Michael Tigar, Selective Service Law Reporter, Judge William Bryant, Resistance Statement, AJ Muste, Carl Bernstein and Washington Post article on "new communities"movement, collective living as way to avoid materialism, working at IPS, "The New Left"published, 60s offered freedom, citizen activism, being part of something bigger than self, "bi-partisan lying" by elected officials enraged young people, Viet Nam War as pulling all movements together, need for humanistic values, understanding role of families in psychology of conflict, work Michael Maccoby.
- Interview: Martel, Erich, 2016 October 28; MS2388
  Erich Martel came to Washington in 1961 to attend Geogetown University. He participated in social causes, joined the Army, later earned a teaching degree and began teaching at an African-American high school. He was active in teachers' unions. His last 25 years of teaching were at Wilson High School where his history classes were legendary and often included visits from activists such as Seymour Hersh.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Erich Martel interview: Erich Martel, career teacher, Georgetown University, 1961, Young Americans for Freedom, Fr. Richard McSorley, GUCAP, tutoring, civil rights, Walter Draude, trip to Selma, Vietnam War, Cardinal Spellman, the draft, Mme Nhu at Georgetown, Army enlistment, OCS, Street Without Joy, Bernard Fall, Trinity College MAT program, Cardozo High School, Wilson High School, Washington Teachers' Union, 1972 teachers' strike, Socialist Workers' Party, anti-war marches, Julius Hobson, political buttons, unions join anti-war efforts, American Federation of Teachers, experts in the classroom, Seymour Hersh, Lt. William Calley, Edward Alvarez, students interview folks at the Vietnam memorial, school administration shortcomings, falsified records, Adrian Fenty.
- Interview: Moore, Douglas E., 2013 April 19; MS2388
  (1928-2019) - Civil rights leader, head of D.C. Black United Front; later, member D.C. Council.
  Keywords provided by the donor for Reverend Douglas Moore interview: Reverend Douglas Moore, North Carolina 1950s, Washington D.C. 1960s and 1970s, First D.C. City Council, Hickory, North Carolina, Uncle's fish market, Howard University, Uncle Oscar Barnes and his market, O Street market, North Carolina fish market, mother as "terrorist", only child, Willard Johnson – Uncle, sold watermelon, Uncle John, Eagle Scout, Hickory Daily Record, Howard University School of Religion, Valedictorian-high school, played football, basketball, civil rights movement in North Carolina, tough grandfather, gun bearer for grandfather, double-barreled shotgun, only black newspaper carrier, farther-high school principal, revolutionary valedictory speech, upset city with speech, Mr. Broome-principal, Reverend J.W. Moore (Jack Moore), audience cheering, North Carolina A&T (Agricultural and Technical), 13th, 14th and 15th amendments to the constitution, Elks oratorical contest, father and mother divorced, father high school principal – Ridgeview High School, Grandfather (Peter Johnson) slapped white policeman, grandfather's shotgun, sit-ins N.C. restaurants, "father of the sit-ins" in N.C., Woolworth's, ice cream parlor, white kids upset by sit-ins, grandfather – Methodist preacher, grandfather taught shooting to white folks, grandfather - "Pete Johnson", "a mean mother fucker", stern, unmovable black men, had shotgun, 2 pistols – 2 .38, arrests Royal Ice Cream Shop – sit-ins, plaque – Royal Ice Cream Shop, SCLC – one of founders, met Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr, at Boston University, King told me "stir up the water", ice cream shop – didn't arrest me, Black United Front, racism in D.C., North Carolina College, Marion Barry, reparations, Rev. George Hart, Columbia Baptist Churches, Jesus, I was "arrogant motherfucker", Christian responsibility, Interview (?) Brooks Todd, Methodist Church, Boston University (B.U.), Howard, Annon (?) Walter Chalmers (?), superior religion teachers at B.U., Marion Barry's women/"the skirts", Donald Graham - "a punk", FBI, black activists, white anti-war activists, racist flyer, knew it was a fake, Julius Hobson, "a radical", cooperated with Hobson, anti-freeway fight, never arrested, scared by my speeches (?), Methodist preacher, Black United Front, I?? Shaw, Walter Fauntroy, Yale, Boston University, Gammon (?), elected first City Council, arrested N.C., Royal Ice Cream Parlor, journalist Chuck Stone, Afro-American, statehood movement, Julius Hobson, D.C. Statehood Party, I am a Marxist, I ain't no atheist, arrests North Carolina, Royal Ice Cream Parlor, arrest – guilty, Peter Johnson, .38, sit-ins, movement disintegrated, civil rights activists, made mark on history, Martin Luther King, Jr., Walter Mueller, Boston University, D.C. Board of Trade, land grab, Shaw U., Gammon, interstate bus, no back of the bus, Doris Hughes Moore – wife, Hickory, N.C., life member, National Rifle Association, NRA, Malcolm X, Howard University takeover, "a bougie takeover", Martin Luther King assassination, SCLC, race war – no, no, no, D.C. MLK riots, kids mad, getting guns, Black revolution impossible, no guns, no money, Black Panther Party – lacked guns, no revolution without guns, Chuck Stone, Jim Lowery, Stokely Carmichael, Miriam Makeba, married Carmichael and Makeba, wrote book, "The Buying and Selling of the D.C. Council", Council "bought", Chuck Stone, Absalom Jordon, Yasser Arafat, FBI, Marion Barry, fluent in French, stored guns, son was marine, FBI, Anthony Williams, ran for mayor, Ku Klux Klan, Stokely Carmichael, NRA, Marion Barry, FBI, Treasury Department, armed revolution – crazy, U.S. Army, police brutality, irrational violence, Howard University, sit-ins, national movement, brutality, Howard University sit-ins, Tuskegee, voter registration, Southwest Georgia, SNCC, Deacons of Defense, married 1998.